What I want to do this afternoon
ما أريد فعله بعد ظهر هذا اليوم
is something a little different than what's scheduled.
شيء مختلف قليلاً عن ما هو مقرر
Foreign policy, you can figure that out
السياسة الخارجية، يمكنكم معرفة ذلك
by watching, I don't know, Rachel Maddow or somebody,
عن طريق المشاهدة، لا أعرف، راتشل مادو أو شخص آخر،
but — (Laughter) —
بل ــ (ضحك)ــ
I want to talk about young people and structure,
أريد أن أتحدث عن الشباب والتنشئة،
young people and structure.
الشباب والتنشئة.
This was last Wednesday afternoon
لقد كان هذا بعد ظهر الأربعاء الماضي
at a school in Brooklyn, New York,
في مدرسة تقع في بروكلن، نيويورك،
at Cristo Rey High School, run by the Jesuits.
في مدرسة كريستو رِي الثانوية، التابعة لليسوعيين.
And I was talking to this group of students, and take a look at them.
وكنت أتحدث لهذه المجموعة من الطلاب، والقيت نظرة عليهم.
They were around me in three directions.
لقد كانوا حولي في ثلاثة توجهات.
You'll noticed that almost all of them are minority.
ستلاحظون على الأغلب أن جميعهم أقلية.
You'll notice that the building is rather austere.
ستلاحظون أن المبنى إلى حدٍ ما بسيط جداً.
It's an old New York school building, nothing fancy.
إنه مبنى مدرسة نيويورك القديمة، ليس شيء فاخر.
They still have old blackboards and whatnot.
لا يزال لديهم سبورات قديمة وغيرها.
And there are about 300 kids in this school,
وهناك حوالي 300 طفل في هذه المدرسة،
and the school's been going now for four years,
والمدرسة مستمرة منذ 4 سنوات،
and they're about to graduate their first class.
وعلى وشك تخرج أول دفعة منها.
Twenty-two people are graduating,
سيتخرج منها 22 شخص،
and all 22 are going to college.
وكلهم سيلتحقون بالكلية.
They all come from homes where there is, for the most part,
كلهم يأتون من المنازل حيث يوجد، بالنسبة لمعظمهم،
just one person in the home,
شخص واحد فقط من كل منزل،
usually the mother or the grandmother, and that's it,
وعادةً تكون الأم أو الجدة، وهذا كل شيء،
and they come here for their education
وتأتي إلى هنا لتعليمهم
and for their structure.
ومن أجل تنشئتهم.
Now I had this picture taken, and it was put up
لدي الآن هذه الصورة التي أُلتقطت ووُضعت
on my Facebook page last week,
على صفحتي في الفيسبوك الأسبوع الماضي،
and somebody wrote in,
وأحد الأشخاص كتب فيها،
"Huh, why does he have him standing at attention like that?"
"هه، لماذا جعله يقف منتبها مثل ذلك؟"
And then they said, "But he looks good." (Laughter)
وبعد ذلك قالوا، "لكنه يبدو جيداً." (ضحك)
He does look good, because kids need structure,
إنه يبدو جيداً لأن الأطفال بحاجة إلى التنشئة،
and the trick I play in all of my school appearances
وطريقتي التي أقوم بها في كل تواجد لي في المدرسة
is that when I get through with my little homily to the kids,
هي أني عند الدخول بموعظتي القصيرة للأطفال،
I then invite them to ask questions,
ثم أدعوهم لتوجيه أسئلة،
and when they raise their hands, I say, "Come up,"
وعندما يرفعوا أيديهم، أقول، "قيام،"
and I make them come up and stand in front of me.
وأطلب منهم القيام والوقوف أمامي.
I make them stand at attention like a soldier.
أطلب منهم القيام بوضعية الإنتباه مثل الجندي.
Put your arms straight down at your side,
ضعوا أيديكم على الجنب بشكلٍ مستقيم،
look up, open your eyes, stare straight ahead,
إنظروا إلى الأمام وافتحوا أعينكم مع التحديق إلى الأمام،
and speak out your question loudly so everybody can hear.
وقولوا أسئلتكم بصوتٍ مرتفع لكي يسمعكم أي شخص.
No slouching, no pants hanging down, none of that stuff.
لا تراخي، ولا بنطلون مرتخي، ولا أي شيء من تلك الأشياء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And this young man, his name is -- his last name Cruz --
وهذا الشاب، أسمه -- أسمه الآخير كروز--
he loved it. That's all over his Facebook page and it's gone viral.
يحب هذا الأسم. ذلك على كل صفحته في الفيسبوك التي انتشرت بسرعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So people think I'm being unkind to this kid.
لذلك الناس يعتقدون أني كنت قاسٍ مع ذلك االولد.
No, we're having a little fun.
كلا، قمنا بالتسلية قليلاً.
And the thing about it, I've done this for years,
وشيء من ذلك أني فعلت هذا لمدة سنوات،
the younger they are, the more fun it is.
وكلما كانوا أصغر كلما كان ذلك مُسلٍ أكثر.
When I get six- and seven-year-olds in a group,
عندما يكون لدي مجموعة أعمارهم 6 و 7 سنوات
I have to figure out how to keep them quiet.
فإن علي أن أعرف كيف أجعلهم هادئين.
You know that they'll always start yakking.
كما تعلمون فإنهم دائماً يبدأون الثرثرة.
And so I play a little game with them
ولذلك فإني العب معهم قليلاً
before I make them stand at attention.
قبل أن أجعلهم يقفون على وضع إنتباه.
I say, "Now listen. In the army,
أقول، "إستمعوا الآن. في الجيش،
when we want you to pay attention,
عندما نريدكم أن تنتبهوا،
we have a command. It's called 'at ease.'
فإنه يكون لدينا أمر.
It means everybody be quiet and pay attention. Listen up.
وتسمى "استرح" وتعني أن كل واحد يبقى هادئاً وفي وضعية الإنتباه. إستمعوا.
Do you understand?"
هل تفهمون؟"
"Uh-huh, uh-huh, uh-huh.""Let's practice. Everybody start chatting."
" أها ، أها , أها." " فلنمارس. كل واحد منهم يبدأ بالتحدث."
And I let them go for about 10 seconds, then I go, "At ease!"
فأتركهم حوالي 10 ثواني ثم أنادي، " استرح!"
"Huh!" (Laughter)
"ها!" (ضحك)
"Yes, General. Yes, General."
" نعم، جنرال. نعم، جنرال."
Try it with your kids. See if it works. (Laughter)
جربوها مع أطفالكم. لاحظوا إذا كانت تفيد. (ضحك)
I don't think so.
لا أعتقد ذلك.
But anyway, it's a game I play, and it comes obviously
ولكن على كل حال، إنها لعبة ألعبها، ومن الواضح أني حصلت عليها
from my military experience.
من خبرتي العسكرية.
Because for the majority of my adult life,
لأني قضيت معظم حياتي عندما كنت شاباً،
I worked with young kids, teenagers with guns, I call them.
عملت مع أطفال صغار، أعتبرهم مراهقين بالنسبة للسلاح.
And we would bring them into the army,
وكنا نحضرهم إلى الجيش،
and the first thing we would do is to put them
وأول شيء نعمله هو أن نهيئ لهم
in an environment of structure, put them in ranks,
بيئة هيكلية، ونجعلهم في رُتَب.
make them all wear the same clothes,
نجعلهم جميعاً يرتدون نفس الملابس،
cut all their hair off so they look alike,
نحلق شعرهم كله ليبدو شكلهم مثل بعض،
make sure that they are standing in ranks.
نتأكد من أنهم يقفون حسب الرتب.
We teach them how to go right face, left face,
نعلهم كيفية الدوران لليمين والشمال.
so they can obey instructions and know
لكي يمتثلوا للتعليمات ويتعرفوا
the consequences of not obeying instructions.
على النتائج المترتبة عن عدم الإمتثال للتعليمات.
It gives them structure.
إنها تمنحهم التنشئة.
And then we introduce them to somebody who they come to hate immediately, the drill sergeant.
ومن ثم نعرفهم على شخص ما ليكرهوه على الفور، رقيب التدريب.
And they hate him.
ويكرهوه.
And the drill sergeant starts screaming at them,
ثم رقيب التدريب يبدأ الصراخ عليهم،
and telling them to do all kinds of awful things.
ويقول لهم أنه سيفعل كل أنواع الأشياء الفضيعة.
But then the most amazing thing happens over time.
لكن بعد ذلك يحدث شيئ مدهش أكثر مع مرور الوقت.
Once that structure is developed,
وحالما تتطور تلك التنشئة،
once they understand the reason for something,
ويفهمون سبب شيءٍ ما،
once they understand, "Mama ain't here, son.
ويفهمون " ماما ليست هنا، يا بُني.
I'm your worst nightmare. I'm your daddy and your mommy.
أنا أسوأ كابوس لك. أنا أبوك وأمك.
And that's just the way it is. You got that, son?
ذلك فقط. أفهمت ذلك، يا بُني؟
Yeah, and then when I ask you a question, there are only three possible answers:
ييه، ومن ثم عندما أسئلك سؤالاً، لا يوجد هناك سوى ثلاث إجابات ممكنة:
yes, sir; no, sir; and no excuse, sir.
نعم، سيدي؛ و لا، سيدي؛ و لا عذر، يا سيدي.
Don't start telling me why you didn't do something.
لا تبدأ بإخباري لماذا لم تعمل شيء ما.
It's yes, sir; no, sir; no excuse, sir."
إنها نعم، سيدي؛ و لا، سيدي؛ و لا عذر، يا سيدي."
"You didn't shave.""But sir —"
" أنت لم تحلق." " لكن يا سيدي ــــــــ"
"No, don't tell me how often you scraped your face this morning.
"لا، لا تقل لي كيف حلقت وجهك هذا الصباح.
I'm telling you you didn't shave."
أنا أخبرك بأنك لم تحلق."
"No excuse, sir.""Attaboy, you're learning fast."
"لا عذر، يا سيدي." "ياه، إنك تتعلم بسرعة."
But you'd be amazed at what you can do with them
لكنك لم تكن مبدعاً في ما استطعت أن تعمل
once you put them in that structure.
عندما تضعهم في تلك التنشئة.
In 18 weeks, they have a skill. They are mature.
خلال 18 اسبوع، سيكون لديهم مهارة. إنهم ناضجون.
And you know what, they come to admire the drill sergeant
وتعلمون ماذا، سيعجبهم رقيب التدريب
and they never forget the drill sergeant.
ولن ينسوا رقيب التدريب.
They come to respect him.
سوف يحترموه.
And so we need more of this kind of structure and respect
ولذلك فإننا بحاجة أكثر إلى هذا النوع من التنشئة والإحترام
in the lives of our children.
في حياة أطفالنا.
I spend a lot of time with youth groups,
أقضي الكثير من الوقت مع مجموعات من الشباب،
and I say to people, "When does the education process begin?"
وأقول للناس، "متى تبدأ العملية التربوية؟"
We're always talking about, "Let's fix the schools.
نتحدث دائما عن، " دعونا نصلح المدارس.
Let's do more for our teachers. Let's put more computers in our schools.
هيا بنا نعمل أكثر من أجل مدرسينا. دعونا نضع أجهزة حاسوب أكثر في مدارسنا.
Let's get it all online."
لنجعل جميع المدارس متصلة بالانترنت."
That isn't the whole answer. It's part of the answer.
تلك ليست الإجابة كاملة. إن ذلك جزء من الإجابة.
But the real answer begins with bringing a child to the school
لكن الإجابة الحقيقية تبدأ بإحضار طفلٍ إلى المدرسة
with structure in that child's heart and soul to begin with.
مع البداية بتنشئة قلب ذلك الطفل وروحه.
When does the learning process begin? Does it begin in first grade?
متى تبدأ عملية التعلم؟ هل تبدأ في الصف الأول؟
No, no, it begins the first time
لا ، لا ، إنها تبدأ في المرة الأولى
a child in a mother's arms
عندما الطفل يكون بين يدي الأم
looks up at the mother
ينظر إلى الأم
and says, "Oh, this must be my mother.
ويقول، " أوه، يجب أن تكون هذه أمي.
She's the one who feeds me.
إنها الشخص الذي يغذيني.
Oh yeah, when I don't feel so good down there,
أوه .. يه، عندما لا أشعر أني جيد،
she takes care of me.
فإنها تعتني بي.
It's her language I will learn."
إنها لغتها التي سأتعلمها."
And at that moment they shut out all the other languages
وفي ذلك الوقت فإنهم يُحرموا من جميع اللغات الأخرى
that they could be learning at that age,
التي يمكن أن يتعلموها في ذلك العمر،
but by three months, that's her.
ولكن لمدة ثلاثة أشهر، لغة الأم فقط.
And if the person doing it, whether it's the mother
وفي حالة أن ذلك الشخص يمارسها، سواءً كانت الأم
or grandmother, whoever's doing it,
أو الجدة، أو اي شخص يمارسها،
that is when the education process begins.
تلك بداية العملية التعليمية.
That's when language begins.
ذلك عند بداية اللغة.
That's when love begins. That's when structure begins.
ذلك عند بداية الحب. ذلك عند بداية التنشئة.
That's when you start to imprint on the child
ذلك عندما تبدأ الغرس في الطفل
that "you are special,
بــ " أنت شيء خاص،
you are different from every other child in the world.
أنت مختلف من أي طفلٍ آخر في العالم.
And we're going to read to you."
ونحن سوف نقرأ لك."
A child who has not been read to
الطفل الذي لم يُقرأ له
is in danger when that child gets to school.
فإنه في خطر عندما يدخل المدرسة.
A child who doesn't know his or her colors
الطفل الذي لا يعرف ألوانه أو ألوانها
or doesn't know how to tell time, doesn't know how to tie shoes,
أو لا يعرف كيف يقول الوقت، لا يعرف كيف يربط الحذاء،
doesn't know how to do those things,
لا يعرف كيف يفعل تلك الأشياء،
and doesn't know how to do something that
ولا يعرف كيف يفعل الشيء الذي
goes by a word that was drilled into me as a kid: mind.
يمر بواسطة كلمة تُغرس فيني كطفل: التفكير
Mind your manners! Mind your adults! Mind what you're saying!
فكر في تصرفاتك! فكر في أخلاقك! فكر في ما تقول!
This is the way children are raised properly.
بهذه الطريقة ينشأ الأطفال بشكلٍ سليم.
And I watched my own young grandchildren now come along
وقد شاهدت أحفادي الآن على نفس المنوال
and they're, much to the distress of my children,
فإنهم، أكثر عرضة للإنزعاج من أطفالي،
they are acting just like we did. You know? You imprint them.
يعملون ما كنا نفعل. تعلمون ذلك؟ إنه تأثيركم عليهم.
And that's what you have to do to prepare children for education and for school.
وذلك هو ما عليكم فعله لإعداد الأطفال للتعليم والمدرسة.
And I'm working at all the energy I have
إني أعمل بكل طاقتي
to sort of communicate this message that
لإيصال هذه الرسالة التي
we need preschool, we need Head Start,
نحتاجها في مرحلة ما قبل المدرسة، نحتاج بداية مبكرة،
we need prenatal care.
نحتاج إلى عناية ما قبل الولادة.
The education process begins even before the child is born,
فالعملية التعليمية تبدأ عادةً قبل ولادة الطفل،
and if you don't do that, you're going to have difficulty.
وإذا لم تقوموا بذلك، فسوف تواجهكم صعوبة.
And we are having difficulties in so many of our communities
لدينا الآن صعوبات في عدد كثير من مجتمعاتنا
and so many of our schools where kids are coming
وعدد كثير من مدارسنا حيث يأتي أطفالنا
to first grade and their eyes are blazing,
إلى الصف الأول وعلامات الفرح في عيونهم،
they've got their little knapsack on and they're ready to go,
وقد حملوا حقائبهم الصغيرة جاهزين للذهاب،
and then they realize they're not like the other first graders
ثم بعد ذلك يتضح لهم أنهم ليسوا كالآخرين في الصفوف الأولى
who know books, have been read to, can do their alphabet.
الذين لديهم الكتب، ويُقرأ لهم، ويعرفون الحروف الأبجدية.
And by the third grade, the kids who didn't have
وعند وصولهم للصف الثالث، فإن الأطفال الذين ليس لديهم
that structure and minding in the beginning
تلك التنشئة والتفكير من البداية
start to realize they're behind, and what do they do?
يبدأون في إدراك أنهم متأخرون، فماذا يعملون؟
They act it out. They act it out, and they're on their way
يتصرفون بطريقتهم. يتصرفون بها حتى تؤدي بهم
to jail or they're on their way to being dropouts.
إلى السجن أو أنهم في طريقهم إلى التسرب.
It's predictable.
يمكن التنبؤ بذلك.
If you're not at the right reading level at third grade,
إذا لم تكن في مستوى القراءة الصحيح عند الصف الثالث،
you are a candidate for jail at age 18,
فإنك مرشح لأن تكون في السجن عند الــ 18 من عمرك،
and we have the highest incarceration rate
حيث لدينا أعلى معدل في السَجْن
because we're not getting our kids the proper start in life.
لأننا لم نرشد أطفالنا إلى البداية السليمة في الحياة.
The last chapter in my book is called
الفصل الأخير من كتابي اسمه
"The Gift of a Good Start."
"هدية البداية الصالحة"
The gift of a good start. Every child ought to have a good start in life.
هدية البداية الصالحة. كل طفل يجب أن يكون لديه بداية صالحة في الحياة.
I was privileged to have that kind of good start.
كان لي الشرف أنه كان لدي نوع من البداية الصالحة.
I was not a great student.
لم أكن طالباً متميز.
I was a public school kid in New York City,
لقد كنت طفلاً في مدرسة عامة في مدينة نيويورك.
and I didn't do well at all.
لم أعمل بشكلٍ جيد مطلقاً.
I have my entire New York City Board of Education transcript
لدي سجلي التعليمي كاملاً الذي حصلت عليه من هيئة التعليم في مدينة نيويورك
from kindergarten through college.
من الروضة وحتى الكلية.
I wanted it when I was writing my first book.
احتجت إليه عند تأليف كتابي الأول.
I wanted to see if my memory was correct,
أردت أن أرى إذا كانت ذاكرتي صحيحة،
and, my God, it was. (Laughter)
و، يا إلهي، لقد كانت بالفعل. (ضحك)
Straight C everywhere.
إن جميع النتائج C.
And I finally bounced through high school,
وفي الأخير تجاوزت المرحلة الثانوية،
got into the City College of New York
ثم التحقت بـ "سيتي كوليج" في نيويورك.
with a 78.3 average, which I shouldn't have been allowed in with,
بمعدل 78.3، الذي كان من المفترض أن لا يُسمح لي الألتحاق بهذه النسبة.
and then I started out in engineering,
ثم بعد ذلك بدأت في الهندسة،
and that only lasted six months. (Laughter)
التي لم تستمر سوى 6 أشهر. (ضحك)
And then I went into geology, "rocks for jocks." This is easy.
ثم حولت إلى الجيولوجيا، "روكس فور جوكس." لعلها سهلة.
And then I found ROTC.
ثم بعد ذلك وجدت ROTC
I found something that I did well and something that I loved doing,
وجدت ما يمكن أن أعمل به أفضل وما أحب،
and I found a group of youngsters like me who felt the same way.
وجدت مجموعة من الشباب الذين شعروا مثلي.
And so my whole life then was dedicated to ROTC and the military.
ولذا فإن حياتي كلها بعد ذلك خصصت لــ ROTC والجيش.
And I say to young kids everywhere, as you're growing up
كما أقول للأطفال الصغار في كل مكان، عندما تكبروا
and as this structure is being developed inside of you,
وعندما هذه التنشئة تتطور فيكم،
always be looking for that which you do well and that which you love doing,
فعليكم البحث دائماً عن ما تُحسنون فعله وما تحبون،
and when you find those two things together, man, you got it.
وعندما تجد شيئين معاً، فإن عليك يا هذا، أن تحصل عليه.
That's what's going on. And that's what I found.
هذا هو ما يحدث. وذلك الذي وجدت.
Now the authorities at CCNY were getting tired of me being there.
الآن سلطات "سيتي كوليج" في نيويورك تعبوا من تواجدي هناك.
I'd been there four and a half going on five years,
فأنا هناك منذُ أربع سنوات ونصف السنة الخامسة،
and my grades were not doing particularly well,
وخصوصاً أن درجاتي لم تكن جيدة،
and I was in occasional difficulties with the administration.
وقد واجهت صعوبات مختلفة مع الإدارة.
And so they said, "But he does so well in ROTC.
ولذلك فإنهم قالوا، " لكنه جيد جداً في ROTC= التدريب العسكري لضباط الإحتياط
Look, he gets straight A's in that but not in anything else."
إنظروا، أن كل درجاته A في ذلك ولكن ليس في شيء غيره."
And so they said, "Look, let's take his ROTC grades
كما أنهم قالوا، "إنظروا، لنأخذ درجاته في ROTC
and roll them into his overall GPA and see what happens."
ونضعها في معدله العام لنرى ماذا يحدث."
And they did, and it brought me up to 2.0. (Laughter)
وقاموا بذلك، ووصل مستواي إلى 2.0. (ضحك)
Yep. (Laughter) (Applause)
صحيح. (ضحك) (تصفيق)
They said, "It's good enough for government work.
لقد قالوا، " إنه جيد بشكلً كافٍ للعمل الحكومي.
Give him to the army. We'll never see him again. We'll never see him again."
أرسلوه للجيش. لن نراه مرةً أخرى. لن نراه مرةً آخرى."
So they shipped me off to the army,
لذلك فقد بعثوني إلى الجيش،
and lo and behold, many years later,
فإذا بهم، بعد عدة سنوات،
I'm considered one of the greatest sons the City College of New York has ever had. (Laughter)
اعتبروني واحداً من أعضم أبناء سيتي كوليج في نيويورك. (ضحك)
So, I tell young people everywhere,
لذلك، أقول للشباب في كل مكان،
it ain't where you start in life, it's what you do with life
المسألة ليس من أين تبدأون، وإنما ماذا تعملون في حياتكم
that determines where you end up in life,
لتقرروا أين ينتهي بكم المطاف في الحياة،
and you are blessed to be living in a country that,
كما أنكم في نعمة عندما تعيشوا في البلاد التي،
no matter where you start, you have opportunities
لا يهم من أين البداية، يكون لكم فيها فرص
so long as you believe in yourself,
مادام أنكم تثقون بأنفسكم،
you believe in the society and the country,
وثقون بمجتمعكم وبلدكم،
and you believe that you can self-improve
كما تثقون بأنكم تستطيعوا تطوير أنفسكم
and educate yourself as you go along.
وتعليم أنفسكم خلال مسيرتكم.
And that's the key to success.
وذلك هو مفتاح النجاح.
But it begins with the gift of a good start.
لكن ذلك يبدأ بهدية البداية الجيدة.
If we don't give that gift to each and every one of our kids,
إذا لم نعطي تلك الهدية لكل واحد من أطفالنا،
if we don't invest at the earliest age,
إذا لم نستثمر بداية العمر،
we're going to be running into difficulties.
فإننا نجري جرياً إلى الصعوبات.
It's why we have a dropout rate of roughly 25 percent overall
إن ذلك هو السبب في حصولنا على نسبة تسرب حوالي 25% من المعدل العام
and almost 50 percent of our minority population
وما يقارب 50% من سكان الأقليات لدينا
living in low-income areas,
يعيشوا في مناطق الدخل المنخفض،
because they're not getting the gift of a good start.
لأنهم لم يحصلو على هدية البداية الجيدة.
My gift of a good start was not only being in a nice family,
هديتي من البداية الجيدة لم تكن فقط لأني كنت في عائلة طيبة،
a good family, but having a family that said to me,
عائلة جيدة، بل لأنه كان لدي العائلة التي قالت لي،
"Now listen, we came to this country in banana boats
"إستمع الآن، جئنا إلى هذه البلاد على قوارب الموز
in 1920 and 1924.
في العام 1920 و 1924.
We worked like dogs down in the garment industry every single day.
وعملنا كل يوم بجهد شاق في صناعة الملابس.
We're not doing it so that you can stick something up your nose
نحن لم نفعل ذلك من أجل أنك ممكن أن تضر نفسك
or get in trouble. And don't even think about dropping out."
أو تقع في مشاكل. فلا تفكر أبداً في ترك المدرسة."
If I had ever gone home and told those immigrant people
كنت دائماً إذا عدت إلى المنزل وقلت للمهاجرين
that, "You know, I'm tired of school and I'm dropping out,"
"كما تعلمون، لقد تعبت من المدرسة وسوف أتركها،"
they'd said, "We're dropping you out. We'll get another kid."
فإنهم يقولون، "سوف نخرجك من المدرسة. سوف يكون لدينا طفل آخر."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They had expectations for all of the cousins
كان لديهم آمال من كافة أبناء العم
and the extended family of immigrants that lived in the South Bronx,
وعائلة المهاجرين المتوارثة التي سكنت في جنوب برونكس،
but they had more than just expectations for us.
لكنهم كان لديهم تطلعات دقيقة أكثر بالنسبة لنا.
They stuck into our hearts like a dagger
فلقد انغرزوا إلى قلوبنا كالخنجر.
a sense of shame: "Don't you shame this family."
شعور بالخجل: "لا تجلب العار لهذه العائلة."
Sometimes I would get in trouble,
أحياناٌ قد أكون في مشكلة،
and my parents were coming home,
ووالديّ قادمَين إلى البيت،
and I was in my room waiting for what's going to happen,
وكنت في غرفتي منتظراً ما سيحدث،
and I would sit there saying to myself, "Okay, look,
وكنت قاعداً هناك قائلاً لنفسي،" أوكيه، إنظروا،
take the belt and hit me, but, God, don't give me that 'shame the family' bit again."
خذوا الحزام واضربوني به، لكن، يا الله، لا تجعلني أجلب أي خزي لهذه العائلة مرةً أُخرى."
It devastated me when my mother did that to me.
لقد دمرتني أمي عندما فعلت ذلك بي.
And I also had this extended network.
وأنا أيضاً لدي هذه الشبكة العائلية المتوارثة.
Children need a network. Children need to be part of a tribe,
الأطفال بحاجة لى شبكة. الأطفال بحاجة لأن يكون جزء من قبيلة،
a family, a community.
عائلة، مجتمع.
In my case it was aunts who lived in all of these tenement buildings.
في حالتي لقد عاشت عماتي في جميع هذه المباني السكنية.
I don't know how many of you are New Yorkers,
لا أعرف كم عدد الذين عاشوا منكم في نيويورك،
but there were these tenement buildings,
لكن هناك تلك المباني السكنية،
and these women were always hanging out one of the windows,
وأولئك النساء اللاتي كنّ دائماً على النوافذ،
leaning on a pillow.
يتكئن على وسائد.
They never left. (Laughter)
إنهن لم يغادرن أبداً. (ضحك)
I, so help me God, I grew up walking those streets,
أنا، بتوفيق من الله، ترعرعت وأنا أمشي على تلك الشوارع،
and they were always there.
وكنت أشاهدهن دائماً هناك.
They never went to the bathroom. They never cooked. (Laughter)
إنهن لم يذهبن للغسيل. ولا إلى الطبخ مطلقاً. (ضحك)
They never did anything.
إنهن لم يفعل شيئاً أبداً.
But what they did was keep us in play.
ما يفعلنه هو إبقائنا في اللعب فقط.
They kept us in play.
لقد أبقتنا في اللعب.
And they didn't care
ولم يكن هناك إهتمام منهن
whether you became a doctor or a lawyer or a general,
سواءً أصبحت دكتور أو محامي أو جنرال،
and they never expected any generals in the family,
ولم يتوقعن أبداً أنه سيكون هناك جنرالات في العائلة،
as long as you got an education and then you got a job.
طالما حصلت على التعليم أو الوظيفة.
"Don't give us any of that self-actualization stuff.
"لا تعطونا أي من تلك الأشياء الي تحقق للذات.
You get a job and get out of the house.
لقد حصلتم على وظائف وتركتم المنزل.
We don't have time to waste for that.
ليس لدينا وقت لنضيعه من أجل ذلك.
And then you can support us. That's the role of you guys."
ثم بعد ذلك فإنكم تستطيعوا دعمنا. إن هذه هي مهمتكم."
And so, it's so essential that we kind of put this culture
ولذلك، فإنه من الضروري أن نكون من النوع الذي يتعامل بهذه الثقافة
back into our families, all families.
بالعودة إلى عائلاتنا، كل العائلات.
And it is so important that all of you here today
كما أنه مهم جداً أن جميعكم اليوم
who are successful people,
الذين هم أشخاص ناجحين،
and I'm sure have wonderful families and children and grandchildren,
وأنا متأكد أن لديكم عائلات، وأبناء، وأحفاد رائعين،
it's not enough. You've got to reach out and back
إن ذلك غير كافٍ. عليكم بالتواصل
and find kids like Mr. Cruz
لتجدوا أطفالاً مثل مستر كروز
who can make it if you give them the structure,
الذين يمكن أن يعملوا ذلك إذا منحتموهم هذه التنشئة،
if you reach back and help, if you mentor,
إذا تواصلتم وتساعدتم، إذا تناصحتم،
if you invest in boys and girls clubs,
إذا قمتم بإستثمار نوادي الأولاد والبنات،
if you work with your school system,
إذا عملتم بنظام مدارسكم،
make sure it's the best school system,
وتأكدوا بأن يكون أفضل نظام مدرسي،
and not just your kid's school, but the school uptown in Harlem,
وليس فقط مدرسة أبنائكم، بل مدرسة أعلى المدينة في حي هارلم،
not just downtown Montessori on the West Side.
وليس فقط أسفل المدينة في حي مونتيسوري الواقع في الغرب.
All of us have to have a commitment to do that.
جميعنا يجب أن يكون ملتزماً بفعل ذلك.
And we're not just investing in the kids.
كما علينا أن لا نستثمر في أطفالنا فقط.
We're investing in our future.
علينا أن نستثمر في مستقبلنا.
We're going to be a minority-majority country
علينا أن نكون بلد الأقلية الأغلبية
in one more generation.
في أكثر من جيلٍ واحد.
Those that we call minorities now are going to be the majority.
أولئك الذيم نقول أنهم أقلية الآن سيكونون أغلبية.
And we have to make sure that they are ready to be the majority.
كما علينا أن نؤكد على أنهم جاهزين لأن يكونوا أغلبية.
We have to make sure they're ready to be the leaders
علينا التأكيد بأنهم مستعدون لأن يكونوا قادة.
of this great country of ours,
لدولتنا العظيمة،
a country that is like no other,
دولةٌ ليس مثلها دولة أخرى،
a country that amazes me every single day,
دولةٌ تذهلني في كل يوم،
a country that's fractious. We're always arguing with each other.
دولةٌ تكون عنيدة. فليناقش كلٌ منا الآخر دائماً.
That's how the system's supposed to work.
تلك الكيفية التي يُفترض أن يعمل النظام بها.
It's a country of such contrasts, but it's a nation of nations.
إنها بلد بتلك الاختلافات، لكنها أمة واحدة من عدة شعوب.
We touch every nation. Every nation touches us.
نتواصل مع كل أمة. وكل أمة تتواصل معنا.
We are a nation of immigrants.
نحن أمة من المهاجرين.
That's why we need sound immigration policy.
لذلك فإننا بحاجة إلى سياسة هجرة متينة.
It's ridiculous not to have a sound immigration policy
من السخرية أن لا يكون لدينا سياسة قوية للهجرة.
to welcome those who want to come here and be part of this great nation,
لنرحب بأولئك الذين يريدون أن يأتوا هنا ويكونوا جزءاً من هذا الشعب العظيم،
or we can send back home with an education
أو نرجعهم بلادهم وقد حصلوا على تعليم
to help their people rise up out of poverty.
ليساعدوا شعوبهم على الإنتفاض من براثن الفقر.
One of the great stories I love to tell is about my love
واحدة من القصص العظيمة التي أحببت أن أخبركم هي عن حبي
of going to my hometown of New York
للذهاب إلى مسقط رأسي نيويورك
and walking up Park Avenue on a beautiful day
وأتمشى في البارك أفينيو في يومٍ جميل
and admiring everything and seeing all the people go by
متعجباً من كل شيء وأرى جميع الناس يمرون من حولي
from all over the world.
وهم من جميع أنحاء العالم.
But what I always have to do is stop at one of the corners
بل إن ما عليّ أن أفعله دوماً هو أن أقف على أحد الزوايا
and get a hot dog from the immigrant pushcart peddler.
وآخذ سندوتش هوت دوغ من أحد الباعة المتجولين المهاجرين.
Gotta have a dirty water dog. (Laughter)
وإضافة توابل الهوت دوغ. (ضحك)
And no matter where I am or what I'm doing,
ولا يهم أين أنا أو ماذا أفعل،
I've got to do that.
كان علي فعل ذلك.
I even did it when I was Secretary of State.
ومع ذلك فعلتها عندما كنت وزيراً للخارجية.
I'd come out of my suite at the Waldorf Astoria
لقد خرجت من الفندق في والدورف أستوريا
— (Laughter) —
ـــــ (ضحك) ــــ
be walking up the street, and I would hit around 55th Street
تمشيت في الشارع، ووصلت حوالي شارع الـ 55
looking for the immigrant pushcart peddler.
باحثاً عن بائع متجول مغترب.
In those days, I had five bodyguards around me
وفي تلك الأيام، كان حولي 5 حراس
and three New York City police cars would roll alongside
وثلاثة من سيارات شرطة نيويورك تدور حول المكان
to make sure nobody whacked me while I was going up Park Avenue. (Laughter)
لضمان عدم إيذائي من أي شخص أثناء جولتي في بارك أفينيو. (ضحك)
And I would order the hot dog from the guy,
وكنت لأطلب سندوتش الـ هوت دوغ من الشخص،
and he'd start to fix it, and then he'd look around
وهو قد بدأت لتجهيزه، ثم نظر إلى
at the bodyguards and the police cars --
الحراس وسيارات الشرطة --
"I've got a green card! I've got a green card!" (Laughter)
"حصلت على البطاقة الخضراء! حصلت على البطاقة الخضراء!" (ضحك)
"It's okay, it's okay."
"أوكيه، أوكيه."
But now I'm alone. I'm alone.
لكن الآن أنا لوحدي. أنا لوحدي.
I've got no bodyguards, I've got no police cars. I've got nothing.
لا يوجد لدي حراس، ولا يوجد سيارات شرطة. لا يوجد لدي أي شيء.
But I gotta have my hot dog.
لكن استطيع الحصول على سندوتش هوت دوغ.
I did it just last week. It was on a Tuesday evening
فعلتها الأسبوع الماضي. كان ذلك مساء يوم الثلاثاء
down by Columbus Circle.
بالقرب من دوار كولومبوس.
And the scene repeats itself so often.
والمشهد يتكرر في كثير من الأحيان.
I'll go up and ask for my hot dog,
سأذهب وأطلب سندوتش هوت دوغ لي،
and the guy will fix it, and as he's finishing,
والشخص سوف يجهزه، وعندما ينتهي،
he'll say, "I know you. I see you on television.
سوف يقول، "أعرفك. شاهدتك في التلفاز.
You're, well, you're General Powell."
أنت، حسناً، أنت الجنرال باول."
"Yes, yes.""Oh ... "
"نعم، نعم." " أوه .."
I hand him the money.
أعطيه النقود.
"No, General. You can't pay me. I've been paid.
"لا ، جنرال. لا يمكن أن تدفع لي. لقد دفعت.
America has paid me. I never forget where I came from.
دفعت لي أمريكا. لن أنسى أبداً من أين أتيت.
But now I'm an American. Sir, thank you."
لكن أنا الآن مواطن أمريكي. شكراً لك يا سيدي."
I accept the generosity, continue up the street,
أقبل الكرم، أستمر ماشياً في الشارع،
and it washes over me, my God,
والنعمة تتدفق عليّ، يا الله،
it's the same country that greeted my parents this way 90 years ago.
إنها نفس البلد التي رحبت بوالدي بنفس الطريقة منذُ 90 سنة.
So we are still that magnificent country,
لذلك فإننا لا نزال تلك الدولة العظيمة،
but we are fueled by young people coming up
بل أن دعمنا هو الشباب القادم
from every land in the world,
من كل أرض في العالم،
and it is our obligation as contributing citizens
كما أنه واجبنا كمواطنين مساهمين
to this wonderful country of ours
إلى هذه الدولة العظيمة
to make sure that no child gets left behind.
لنؤكد أنه لا طفل يُترك خلفنا.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)